A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Graphic Services, Early History FA931
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Graphic Services, Early History
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University Press
FA931
2 Cubic Feet 2 boxes and 1 package.
2 boxes and 1 package.
Biographical/Historical note
In order to assist in the dissemination of scientific investigations conducted at the Institute and elsewhere, publication was an early and important activity of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. A senior member of the scientific staff was usually the editor of a periodical. As early as 1910 the Institute had a Publication Service, which was supervised from 1910 by Editha C. Campbell until she retired in the fall of 1940. A Department of Illustration and Photography was under a part-time arrangement with De. Eduard Learning from 1906 until 1910 when Louis Schmidt undertook the direction of a full-time department. Louis Schmidt was at the head of the department until he reached the age of 70 in 1936. The work in the Department of Illustrations included hand-drawn illustrations for publications, photographs, moving pictures of experimental procedures made for the various investigators and used for a variety of purposes. Louis Schmidt served on a consultant basis until his death in 1939. Joseph Blauvelt Haulenbeek was acting in charge of Illustrations during that time and named officially in charge of illustrations in 1942, serving until he resigned September 1, 1946. Julian Alexander Carlile who was in charge of illustrations in the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology at Princeton took charge of the New York Department starting October 1, 1947 and divided his time between the two departments until they were consolidated during 1950. He directed the expanding department until his death in 1959 when he was succeeded by Richard F. Carter until 1964. In the academic year 1968/1969 Lewis William Koster became Manager of Graphic Services until 1973. March 1973 Bill Leyrer was appointed to that position.
Florence M. Stewart succeeded Editha Campbell in charge of the Publication Service in 1940 and served until she retired June 30, 1963, when she was succeeded by Margaret E. Broadbent.
Effective January 1, 1957 Charles Irvin Campbell was appointed Administrative Associate for Information Services. He had responsibility for a variety of information services among which were Secretary of the Library Committee, Librarian, ex officio, and supervision of the Publication Service and Illustration and Duplicating Services. Included were publication duties of such items as the Annual Report, Rockefeller Institute Quarterly, and the Calendar of Events. On October 20, 1958 the Board of Trustees approved a cooperative arrangement with the Oxford University Press to assist in producing, advertising and selling publications of the newly established Rockefeller Institute Press. The plan was for the Institute to continue publishing journals in accord with previously established policy and arrangements. Charles I. Campbell was appointed Director of The Rockefeller Institute Press. The Publications Service became the Journals Department without change of personnel or function. A new Books and Reports Department was created with responsibility for the production of books and the publication of bulletins and reports issued by the Institute.
January 1, 1960 Reynard F. Biemiller was appointed Assistant Director of The Rockefeller Institute Press. Effective December 5, 1960 Raymond B. Griffiths was appointed to the newly created position of Executive Editor of the Journal of Cell Biology.
Charles I. Campbell resigned May 15, 1962 and Joseph G. Sutton served as Acting Director of the Press from January 1963 until in 1964 William Arthur Bayless was named Director of the Press.
William Bayless retired as Director of The Rockefeller University Press on February 8, 1980. As of February 11, 1980, Mrs. Helene Jordan agreed to serve as acting director of the Press.
Effective July 1, 1980, Mrs. Helene Jordan was appointed Director of The Rockefeller University Press.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 520
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Related Materials
See: RU News and Notes, 5 (Dec 1973) p.4 "Ruth Mandlebaum Retires." for information.
Scope and Contents
Contains photos and office files.
Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medical sciences; Life sciences; Medical technology; Science -- Study and teaching; Medicine, Preventive; Biology -- Research; Medical research; Medical education
- Louis Schmidt material
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Received from Ruth Mandlebaum, 17 June 1985, in Mrs. Mirsky's office.
  - Biographical, 5" Legal (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Portrait of L. Schmidt in lab coat, undated
    - World War I certificate of appreciation from Department of the Navy (Franklin D. Roosevelt, Asst. Secretary of the Navy)
  - Christmas card design for Rufus Cole, 5" Legal (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    (see also package)
  - Engravings (small), 5" Legal (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts, 5" Legal (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Doctor Wickliffe Rose retirement, Rockefeller Foundation appreciation, 1 page
    - Theobald Smith memorial minute, 1935 April 20; 12 pp.
  - Paintings of flowers for Henry A. Dreer, Philadelphia [Printed pages], 5" Legal (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rivers, Thomas M. "Virus de Vejez" Photocopy of humorous (11 items) presentation at meeting of The Society of American Bacteriologists, New York, December 1935, 11 pp. 7 negatives of figures 1-7; 3 prints of figures 5-7, 1935 December; 5" Legal (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellany; unidentified color illustration (scientific), 5" Legal (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Metal plates for engravings, 5" Legal (Box 1, Folder 8)
    High Bridge.
    On Lake Gorda (sp?)
  - (L. Schmidt/R. Mandlebaum op. cit.), 5" Legal
    - Watercolors: Iris; Lake with trees; flowers (carnations?), 5" Legal 3 items (Package 1, Folder 1)
    - Large engravings, 5" Legal 5 items (Package 1, Folder 2)
    - Christmas, 5" Legal (Package 1, Folder 3)
      Photograph of entranceway (to Schmidt house?) (2 items)
      Holly border for Rufus Cole card design.
  - GLASS NEGATIVE Honor roll of DeWitt Clinton School in the Great War, 1917-1919; 5" Legal (Box 2)
- Material from Ruth Mandlebaum, 5" Legal
  Includes items by Louis Schmidt.
  Custodial History note
  Delivered by Helen Mandlebaum Vogel to Mrs. Sonya W. Mirsky, 17 July 1986.
  - Photographs, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Simon Flexner seated in laboratory.
    Abraham Flexner, portrait of.
  - Photograph of Karl Landsteiner plaque, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hideyo Noguchi, 2 photographs (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Noguchi gravesite at Woodlawn Cemetery, 1 photograph (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rivers, Thomas M, 3 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes:
    - Portrait by Louis Schmidt. Inscribed: "Best Wishes to 'The Boss' of the Illustration Department. Thomas M. Rivers 1932"
    - Portrait. Different portrait. Inscribed: "To my friend Helen Mandlebaum. Thomas M. Rivers 1932"
    - Group photograph in Guam, WWII. Admiral Nimitz and T.M. Rivers identified
  - Mounted photograph of drawing in color by Colinkin, 1 items (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes T.M. Rivers and D.D. Van Slyke on tennis court at RI
    Used as cover of Physician's Bulletin, May-June 1948 issue.
- Photographs, 5" Legal
  - RIMR-RI-RU Heads of Illustration Department. Composite, 1910-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mounted photograph of sign in Illustration Division with motto, "Ours not to reason why Ours but to do or die" (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Note on back of photo by R.J.M. [Ruth Mandlebaum] stating that original of this drawn in color by R.J.M. and hung in Illustration/Graphic Services
    Location of original not known. See note on back of photograph for further explanation.
  - Reprint. Inscribed: "Ruth. J.B. Haulenbeek", 1 item (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Schmidt, L. and Haulenbeek, J.B. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The photography of glass apparatus (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Journal of the Biological Photographic Association 5 (1937) 185-189. Pages 186-187 contain photographs of The Lindbergh Perfusion pump developed in collaboration with Alexis Carrel, which this article is about (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence and telephone reply between M.W. Chase, Ruth Mandlebaum, and Richard Carter, 1982 February; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - M.W. Chase/Ruth Mandlebaum, 1982 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    re Enclosure:
  - "Memo, Telephone reply from Richard Carter to my [MWC] letter of late 1981" Giving some history of Illustration Division, 1982 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - R. Mandlebaum/M.W. Chase. Reply to Dr. Chase with comments, corrections, and additions to history of Illustration Division, 1982 February 21; 2 pp. handwritten letter. Signed "R.J.M." (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Illustrations of apparatus, primarily drawings. Most are untitled, 14 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Identified drawings include:
    "Extraction chamber of Van Slyke-Neill Manometric Apparatus (J. Biol. Chem., 1924, 61, 523)".
    Also drawings of what appear to be diagrams of amino acid analyzer of Moore and Stein [tentative identification].
  - Charts, graphs and tables (with titles), 14 items (Box 1, Folder 18)
    "Acute lymphatic leukemia transferred from a D.B.A. injected rat"
    "Calculation of blood volume from the change in blood gravity due to infusion of plasma or similar fluid, "
    "The chemical structure of ribonuclease from The Rockefeller University" [Chromatographic separations]
    "Classification of proteolytic enzymes by their specificity"
    "Comparison of chemical structures of compounds known to be active or inactive against rickettsial infections"
    ["The hydrolysis of TL146..." 8 figures on 2 sheets]
    "Incidence of tumors after methylcholanthrene"
    "Life cycle of Chlamydomonas Reinhardi"
    "Line chart for calculating plasma proteins, hemoglobin and hematocrit from gravities of plasma and blood"
    "Line chart for calculating percentages of normal plasma proteins and hemoglobin from gravities of plasma and blood"
    "Reaction time for amino nitrogen with nitrous acid"
    "Results of implantation of Brown-Pearce tumor cells into immunized rabbits"
  - Miscellaneous charts, tables, and graphs (untitled), 5 items (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Typescript note entitled "'The Mountain'" attached to Louis Schmidt etching - see below, framed print #3, 1 item (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 4 framed etchings by Louis Schmidt, oversize
    Conditions Governing Access
    Material is unavailable.
    - 1. 1928 East River view with 59th St. Bridge
      Item is unavailable.
    - 2. 1928 River scene - lower Manhattan?
    - 3. 1929 Street scene - Lower Manhattan
    - 4. East River and New York Hospital, undated
  - Announcements, 1978; ½" Hollinger (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Manual, [1977?] (Box 2, Folder 2)